few ideas can polarize like socialism
many see it as the path to Freedom manu
others see it as the path to tyranny
this video won't pick sides in that
debate we're only here to answer the
question what is it what is
socialism many would say that the answer
is simple and they'd open a dictionary
and read a definition about socialism
being the government owning the means of
production and directing the economy
that's definitely a significant
understanding of socialism but the
problem is it's tied to a certain era
and many if not most of modern
socialists don't go by it so we're going
to need something broader but then if
you ask those socialists what they think
socialism is their answer is often
unusably broad like saying socialism is
the Hope for human freedom and justice
under the unprecedented conditions of
life that Humanity will face in the 21st
century so by that pretty much anyone
can be a socialist this is the point
where people usually do a lot of hening
about how difficult it is to nail down a
specific conception of socialism I
frankly don't think it's that bad I
think the best way to do this is to go
through socialism chronologically show
where the ideas came from where they
converged and where they split and where
that leaves us today so most of this
video is basically going to be a history
of socialist thought I think it'll help
to start with some general comments the
first thing to say is that socialism as
a political tradition emerged as a
reaction against liberalism specifically
as a reaction against the Industrial
Revolution as liberalism grew in
popularity and in influence socialism
grew along with it so the histories of
liberalism and socialism are intertwined
and you can even think of liberalism as
a parent ideology of socialism
liberalism can be understood as the
political philosophy where individuals
are held to be ends in themselves
liberals want to create a political
order where people can develop into
whoever they want to be they can think
whatever they want to think believe
believe whatever they want to believe
and pursue whatever they want to pursue
liberals primarily achieve that through
law notably by granting people rights
those rights are designed to keep people
from suppressing each other's
individuality liberalism expressed as an
economic philosophy is capitalism so
that's when you have property rights
backed by law and at least theoretically
a free market where people are free to
exchange goods and services with others
in a liberal order hierarchies naturally
develop and socialists traditionally
concern themselves with negative effects
related to those hierarchies Liberals
are traditionally concerned with
concentrations of political power so
they don't want a king to have all the
power they don't want a minority to have
all the power and they don't want a
majority to have all the power so they
want Power broken up across Society
socialists are traditionally concerned
with concentrations of economic power
typically the power that the rich are
thought to hold over the poor so
socialists typically want their own
checks and Balan
against concentrations of economic power
the Socialist ethic aspires towards
equalitarianism which can also be called
egalitarianism but I think
equalitarianism is a word that's a
little bit easier to intuitively grasp
what exactly that means depends on the
Socialist it could mean that people
should get equal portions of things or
it could mean that people in some other
way should be treated equally or it
could just mean the general belief that
human beings have fundamentally equal
Worth or moral status so the concept of
equality is very important in socialism
socialists tend to be motivated by a
sense of Injustice they tend to look to
the worst off the needy the sick the
unfortunate or the oppressed and claim
that their circumstances are unnecessary
and even unfair people typically point
to three founding influences of
socialism s Simone Charles Fier and
Robert Owen what they all had in common
was a sense of the inadequacy of of
unadulterated liberalism which is to say
unregulated capitalism they didn't call
themselves socialists because the word
socialism wasn't around yet but you can
see something recognizably socialist in
their work for example when s Simone
looked around 18th century France he
said here is an idea that seems right to
me the first needs of Life are the most
urgent ones those without property can
only satisfy them in an incomplete
manner a physiologist sees clearly that
their most constant desire should be
that of lowering their taxes or
increasing in their pay which amounts to
the same thing s Simone called for the
creation of a new Christianity founded
on the principle that all men must
behave as brothers toward one another
and whose overall goal was the most
rapid possible amelioration of the
condition of the poorest class he also
advocated for collectively agreeing on
rewarding those who succeed in doing
works of General utility for example by
rewarding in the artists who fill the
gaps in your busy life with the
pleasures which are best suited to
develop your intelligence in other words
he's saying that if we let things freely
develop negative side effects come along
with that and he's arguing that we
should instead intentionally shape
things according to our values going
forward that's going to be a running
theme in socialism Charles Fier looked
at capitalist societies and argued that
they weren't organized efficiently he
thought immense advantages would result
if people were brought together to work
communally he said why are there 300
wineries competing against each other
most of them in disrepair when there
could be one great wiery why would a 100
milkmaids go to the neighboring City to
get a 100 jugs of milk when one milkid
could go get a barrel of milk for
everybody so if we did these things
collectively according to Fier they
wouldn't be so wasteful Fier also
thought that capitalist societies had
unnecessarily depressing work lives and
he thought we could reorganize our work
lives in a way that would make people
more passionate for example you could
divide people up into teams and have
them compete against each other for
honors or rotate jobs throughout the day
so no one has to work for more than a
couple hours in any role he thought you
didn't have to force people to do this
stuff if a few intentional communities
first set an example he thought others
would follow they would be brought
together by a lure of gain and Pleasures
as he put it if a unified Society
produced three times as much as an
atomized Society people would be
incentivized to unify Robert Owen had a
theory that people were products of
their environment and as such he thought
we should use our resources to make
people better make them happier make
them Kinder better mannered and more
productive he thought the best place to
do that would be through education when
people are young and impressionable and
he specifically saw the government as a
means to that end Owen thought
governments should establish rational
plans for the education and general
formation of the characters of their
subjects focusing on forming their
character in childhood which he thought
would prevent bad habits from forming
like lying or Waning to hurt others and
he thought it would promote good habits
like waning to help others this is
essentially a reaction against the
individualism of liberalism so liberals
tend to think that if you're doing well
in life or if you're doing badly in life
it's your own fault and here he's
flipping that he's saying it's not
necessarily the indiv ual's fault but
rather it's the fault of the environment
Owen thought that this explained the
squalid conditions of the poor saying
shall the well-being of millions of the
poor half naked half famished untaught
and untrained daily increasing to a most
alarming extent in these islands not
call Forth One petition one delegate or
one rational effective legislative
measure no for such has been our
education Owen also believed that happy
employees are more productive
he set up a community that paid
unusually high wages that also had
Pleasant working conditions and had
comfortable homes for the workers these
are just a few of their arguments that
shaped socialism going forward looked at
more fully none of them were properly
socialists as we understand the word now
for example when s Simone imagined
himself addressing the working class he
wrote we are 10 times 20 times 100 times
more numerous than the possessors and
yet the possessors wield over us a
domination far greater than any power we
have over them then he says I realize my
friends how entirely frustrated you are
but note that the possessors although
inferior in number possess more
Enlightenment than you and that for the
general good domination must be
distributed according to the share of
intelligence look at what happened in
France while your comrades were dominant
there they produced a famine I think
this illustrates that we have since then
established a definitive idea of what is
and is not socialist so you should be
able ble to look at what s Simon said
and see exactly where it jumped ship and
isn't socialist anymore and that's where
he accepts hierarchies and even frames
them as being natural and even for the
greater good the Socialist conception of
equalitarianism means that socialists
want to mitigate hierarchies they
probably don't want to frame them as
being natural and they especially don't
want to frame them as being for the
greater good a major figure that
solidified that conception of
equalitarianism is a man named babou who
wrote Under the name graas so he
sometimes called graas babou babou
emerged during the French Revolution
while the revolutionaries were trying to
figure out how to order their new
Society the French revolution's ethic
was based on the twin principles of
Liberty and equality the word fraternity
was in there too but Liberty and
equality were their main principles the
philosopher John ja rouso was an
influence on the French Revolution on
the whole but his social contract and
discourse on inequality were especially
an influence on babo who saw himself as
simply implementing Russo's theories
babou came forward and wanted the
revolutionaries to take the word
equality much more seriously he wanted
their new Society to settle for nothing
less than perfect class equality he
wanted for all individuals without
distinction an absolutely equal portion
of all the goods since men are
absolutely equal Babu fruit they must
not have any private possessions but
must enjoy everything in common so that
no one can by the mere fact of birth be
either more or less rich or be
considered less worthy than any of those
around him which makes babou arguably
the founder of modern communism this was
explicitly intended to end class
distinctions baban his associates made
that clear in their Manifesto of the
equals where they said let it come to
end at last this great Scandal that our
posterity will never believe disappear
at last revolting distinctions between
rich and poor great and small Masters
and servants Governors and governed let
there be no differences between human
beings other than those of age and sex
babou also brought a revolutionary
ideology to socialism which means you
want a sudden thorough transformation of
society typically by seizing power babo
and his associates plotted to take over
the Revolution and Lead it themselves
making them the first to imagine
Revolution as a calculated process
directed by a Vanguard of cons
conspirators whose goals might be
unknown to the mass of their followers
this might be reminding you of a later
socialist who had actually successfully
do that and who will get to bab's plot
was discovered by the revolutionaries
they weren't in a forgiving mood so that
was the end of babo but he would live on
as an influence for Communists who would
emerge after him in Europe This is Bab
being referenced in The Communist
Manifesto the term socialism was coined
by the followers of Robert Owen in the
18 20s as capitalism developed through
the early to mid 1800s it became
increasingly industrialized and with
that class distinctions sharpened a
self-conscious industrial working class
began to take shape in England and
Western Europe new types of socialists
emerged that framed their theories
through class conflict the socioeconomic
halves against the socioeconomic have
knots and they specifically saw the have
knots as being the industrial working
class who they called the proletariat
but these socialists tended to be middle
class and they saw themselves as needing
to lead and educate the working class
one of those was Louis blany who said
the poor man does not know the source of
his ills ignorance the daughter of
subjection makes him into the docile
instrument of the privileged crushed by
toil a stranger to the intellectual life
what can he know about these social
phenomena in which he plays the role of
the Beast of Burden another leading
socialists that emerged was Pierre
Joseph prudon he wanted a society based
in mutualism which is essentially an
anarchist Society a society with no
government where workers sell their
labor to each other there were many
other thinkers during that time period
like Louis Blanc who wanted to extend
voting rights to the working class but
none of these are names that people
really know anymore in the mid 1800s one
figure rose up and dominated socialism
with his ideas easily becoming the
biggest figure in the tradition and that
of course is KL Marx Marx came from a
philosophical tradition of system
building which was popular up until his
time but isn't really done anymore so
system building is when you make an
elaborate self-contained body of work
that tries to explain just about
everything as bertron Russell put it
Marx was the last of the great system
Builders I think this brought an
intellectual grandiosity to socialism
that hasn't been matched since there
were all these separate socialist ideas
floating around at the time that had
mostly come from France and England and
what Marx did was to combin them
together with a German philosophy
popular in his time which was the
philosophy of gorg Hegel I'm going to
spend some time laying this out because
it's crucial to understanding what Marx
brought to socialism and it's also
crucial to understanding what happened
to socialism going forward Marx was
influenced by Hegel who was influenced
by Aristotle who was influenced by Plato
all four were system Builders with
Aristotle and Plato there's only one
aspect of their thought that we're
concerned with here and that's their
idea of essence Plato was interested in
the difference between universals and
particulars for example think of the
word cat just the abstract concept of a
cat it's not any one cat in particular
it transcends them it's a universal
concept an ideal cat any one particular
cat for Plato is always made imp
perfectly in the image of the ideal cat
so the ideal cat contains the essence of
cat which we could call cattiness it's
an Essence that exists outside of
particular cats it exists before they do
when they come into existence it shapes
their size their health their strength
and also their behavior for example
Plato thought these Essences explained
why like things gravitate toward one
another a rock dropped Falls to be with
other rocks rocks Fire Rises to be with
a each thing has a tendency to be toward
its Kindred element that tendency makes
the heavy go down and the light go up
Aristotle seemed to believe that he was
updating Plato's Essence by claiming
that it's not external but inside you
it's what you are by your very nature
Aristotelian Essences are things that
you can't change and still be you like
your Humanity for example these essences
shap shape your properties and your
potentialities they shape how you look
and how you feel and also how you move
and how you behave through these
Essences things possess the principle of
motion in themselves Aristotle used that
to develop his theory of natural places
if things are removed from their natural
place because of these Essences they
have a tendency to return to it also for
Aristotle Essence can precede existence
he said things can subsist as a sort of
potential energy before they become
actualized before a house is built for
example it was fit for being built the
fact that it was fit for being built
acts as an essential cause that builds
the house we're talking about ancient
philosophy here part of this was an
attempt to explain the world before the
discovery of genes and before Newtonian
physics around Newton's time things
started to sharpen and become less
mystical but even that was a slow
gradual change so Western philosophy was
differential to Aristotle and Plato for
some 2,000 years after their time as a
result the notion of essence was an
intimate part of every Western
philosophy subsequent to Aristotle until
we came to Modern Times gor Hegel
writing in early 1800s Prussia was in
that sense a pre-modern thinker he took
Aristotle's notion of essence and
applied it to history he wanted to
answer the question what is the ultimate
design of the world and he answered that
due to these hidden undeveloped Essences
the world had a principle it had a plan
of existence a law and that law was a
law of historical progress a progression
from the imperfect towards the more
perfect as evidence he pointed to the
spreading of Freedom over time and
pointed to the Prussian monarchy where
he lived as a place where all had
finally achieved Freedom it's a
redefinition of the word Freedom so if
that was confusing to you I wouldn't
lose sleep over it the point is that
Hegel thought that these hidden
undeveloped Essences brought an
inexorable logic to the history of the
world and that was to make it move over
time towards this increasing Perfection
and for Hegel this was both an ethical
and a logical Perfection Hegel thought
that the spirit of nations were
ultimately the drivers of History they
drove history forward so hegel's
philosophy was ultimately nationalist
Marx grew up studying Hegel so he wanted
to take hegel's ideas and place them in
an updated socialist context during
Marx's time Enlightenment values were
spreading and hegel's idea that the
world was driven forward by Spirit was
too mystical for Marx so he preferred to
base his theory in matter literally
physical stuff specifically physical
stuff that relates to the economy and
our ability to provide for ourselves
like land and coal and machines so Marx
called those material conditions and
believed that they determined deted the
kind of economy we have as he put it the
windmill gives you Society with the
feudal Lord the steam Mill Society with
the industrial capitalist you can call
the type of economy we have like a
capitalist one our mode of production
and then Mark says the mode of
production in material life determines
the general character of the social
political and spiritual processes of
life so for Marx everything stems from
Material conditions the material
conditions create capitalism and from
there you have the way we think our
culture our law politics Society so as
material conditions change society
changes along with them unlike Adam
Smith who saw capitalism as bringing
people together into voluntary and
mutually beneficial relationships Carl
Marx saw antagonism when he looked at
capitalism he saw involuntary labor and
class conflict lower class people had to
work if they didn't they would starve if
you asked workers ERS how much they
wanted to be paid their answer would be
as much as possible but if you asked
bosses how much they should pay the
workers the bosses would answer as
little as possible also if you ask these
bosses how hard they should work these
workers the answer would be as hard as
possible after all they had other
businesses to compete with Marx like
Hegel believed that history was
Progressive and he believed that class
conflict drove that historical
progression so classes were for Marks
what nations were for Hegel as Marx
wrote the history of all hitherto
existing Society is the history of class
struggles Freeman and slave Patrician
and plebian Lord and Surf guildmaster
and journeyman in a word oppressor and
oppressed stood in constant opposition
to one another carried on an
uninterrupted Now hidden now open fight
a fight that each time ended either in a
revolutionary reconstitution of society
at large or in the common ruin of the
contending classes when one class wins a
class struggle according to this Theory
a new Society is created so when
middleclass Journeymen won power against
Guild Masters and implemented modern
property rights feudalism ended and
capitalism began and again he argued
that the underlying Force here is
changing material conditions he argued
that it was time for feudalism to go
Marx believed that the new societies
were preferable to the ones that came
before for example he credits the
Bourgeois who are the property owning
class in capitalism with creating
enormous cities which greatly increased
the urban population as compared with
the rural and thus rescued a
considerable part of the population from
the idiocy of rural life but Marx still
fundamentally condemned the capitalism
of his time and the society that came
along with it this was a time when
capitalism was mostly unregulated so he
had child labor and you had longer hours
and low pay and and dangerous conditions
the lowest paid workers at the time were
working for subsistence wages which
means that they were barely making
enough to be able to feed themselves
Marx didn't leave his feelings about
these things up for interpretation he
found it morally horrifying he pointed
out average life expectancies for the
working class around Urban England where
he did most of his writing in Manchester
it was 17 years in Liverpool it was just
15 he believed that the problem was the
legal right to own private property by
that he mostly meant property relating
to Industry so it could be factories
could be machines could be products
coming out of a company or the
intellectual property of a company
itself so private property for Marks is
mostly property relating to Industry and
in his analysis he broke capitalist
societies down into two main classes you
had the bisi who owned private property
and you had the proletariat who were
propertyless industrial workers he
thought the right to own private
property gave the bourgeois Supreme
political power in capitalist societies
making them the ruling class what we
would normally call liberal Society to
him was Bourgeois Society so he thought
the law morality and religion coming
from capitalist societies reflected
Bourgeois prejudices and Bourgeois
interests it's not clear how aware Marx
was of the implications of this next
part but he crucially took an idea of
Hegel and applied it to his theory and
that's hegel's idea that due to a hidden
developed Essence human societies had a
law of historical development like Hegel
he believed Society was inexorably
moving towards an increasing Perfection
and also like Hegel this was both an
ethical and a logical Perfection he said
if the conflict hinges on the right to
own private property and if the people
without property far outnumber the
people with property then the solution
is for the propertyless masses to
realize their common oppression than to
ban together rise up seize power and
Implement a new Society a communist
Society where the right to own private
property is abolished which he thought
would finally break the historical Saga
of class Conflict by being the first
Society without class conflict as he
wrote in his 20s communism is the riddle
of History solved and it knows itself to
be this solution as markx got older he
toned down that kind of mystical talk
but his historicist conviction and his
support for communism remained the fall
of capitalism and the rise of Communism
he maintained was inevitable this is an
end of History kind of argument he's
saying that capitalism is the last form
of society to feature class conflict and
that communism will be the first Society
without class conflict which will bring
on a new era of History so everything up
until that to Marks is prehistory I
think this is a good time to nail down
what communism is communism is a type of
socialism so socialism is the broad
tradition and communism is a specific
variant of the mainstream types of
socialism communism is probably the
furthest to the left it has three main
features one is the abolition of private
property which is at least any kind of
property relating to Industry which is
also called the means of production the
second feature is its goal it wants to
abolish class distinctions so the goal
is a society with no class inequality in
Marx's writing the dictatorship of the
proletariat holds power which is his
term for the Communist working class
once they take power although he never
clearly articulated what that means or
what that looks like one important thing
he did say was to say that the
dictatorship of the proletariat was to
take all capital from the Bourgeois and
to place all instruments of production
in the hands of the state what's
supposed to happen from there is a
matter of debate Marx saw communism as
an international movement which would
transcend nationality and eventually
sweep the world which led to a history
of international aspirations in
communism and even socialism more
broadly but I think it's worth saying
that this hasn't been consistent in
practice even Marx himself leaned into
nationalism when times seemed to call
for it Marx thought communism would
develop in stages he thought there'd be
a lower stage where he'd still have
wealth inequality since people don't
have equal needs or ability to work but
he seemed to think that in a higher
stage of communist Society all Goods
would be publicly owned and wealth
distinctions and perhaps money itself
would disappear as he wrote once all the
Springs of Cooperative wealth flow more
abundantly only then can the narrow
Horizon of Bourgeois right be crossed in
its entirety and Society inscribe on its
banners from each according to his
ability to each according to his needs
marks thought in that kind of society
where the public had control over
resources people would have more freedom
to choose what they want to do in their
work lives so he thought people wouldn't
be forced to specialize like they often
are in capitalist societies he thought
people would be free to do one thing
today and another tomorrow to hunt in
the morning fish in the afternoon rear
cattle in the evening or criticize after
dinner although that last bit was
probably a joke on his part markx
refrained from elaborating much more on
his vision for communism he said he
didn't want to write receipts for the
cook shops of the future he instead
spent most of his writing criticizing
his competitors and laying out his
economic theory that we mostly see in
capital which he believed proved the
inevitable fall of capitalism and Rise
of Communism as he wrote Capital aimed
to lay be the economic law of motion of
modern society his theory essentially
claims that in capitalism business
owners extract as much profit as they
possibly can from their workers while
paying them as little as they can back
in return the business owners then take
those profits and use them to expand
their businesses Buy more machines and
develop technology which further
develops the material conditions of
capitalism as this continues and
business owners compete with each other
and push everyone else's wages down as
Marx described it a few winners would
emerge and the great masses would be
pushed down into poverty and subsistence
wages Marx described this as two large
polls developing on one end you have the
accumulation of wealth which again was
supposed to be into fewer and fewer
hands and on the other end you have an
accumulation of misery Agony of toil
slavery ignorance brutality mental
degradation he said that as there was
this growing mass of misery there'd be a
corresponding growing revolutionary
impulse an eventual Revolt of the
working class as material conditions and
the social conditions that correspond to
them continued to develop in that manner
they eventually outgrow capitalism
bursting it like a shell once that
happened he thought a revolution would
occur as he wrote The Nail of capitalist
private properties sounds the
expropriators are expropriated so with
that the die was cast I think that
aspect of marks has since been
downplayed but at the time it was the
centerpiece of Marxism the question was
will it happen or won't it happen in the
decades following Marx's death
capitalism seemed to be developing in
the way that Marx predicted class
Dynamics seemed to be polarizing and
sharpening Marxist parties sprang up
across Europe and the German Socialist
Party emerged as an international leader
of socialism and was explicitly Marxist
it occupied an increasing number of
seats in the local state and National
legislatures controlled immense trade
unions and was exceedingly welld
disciplined and organized acting in the
belief that marxian sociology provided
irrefutable Assurance of its ultimate
Triumph but in the last decade of the
19th century ominous contradictions to
Marxism began to appear capitalism was
reforming and becoming gentler misery
wasn't increasing it seemed to be
shrinking wealth was spreading across
all classes of society and the working
class didn't seem to be turning towards
communism marxists were faced with a
choice stick with the position that Marx
was right which was the Orthodox Marxist
position or say that at least in some
aspects he was wrong which implies
diversifying your sources of belief the
person who came to embody the latter
position was a man named Edward
Bernstein Bernstein was a highly
regarded Marxist he was mentored by
Marx's collaborator frederck angles he
was even asked by Engles to produce a
new volume of capital based on Marx's
notes But as time went on these Trends
troubled Bernstein and they reached a
point where he couldn't reconcile them
with his commitment to Marx anymore he
wrote a book called evolutionary
socialism as an extended critique on
Marx that brought about a split in
socialism that Still Remains to this day
marxists at the time gave Bernstein's
views a name revisionism to show that
the historical Trend that Marx predicted
wasn't occurring Bernstein checked
certain statements in capital against
modern evidence like tax receipts and
concludes that it is quite wrong to
assume that the present development of
society shows a relative or indeed
absolute diminution of the number of the
members of the possessing classes their
number increases both relatively and
absolutely if you just looked at what
was happening in society he argued
Improvement was unmistakable Society was
transforming in a Humane Direction which
signifies not hopelessness but
capability of improvement in the
condition of the worker he said it is
not only useless it is the greatest
Folly to attempt to conceal this from
ourselves he also broke from Marx as a
theorist for example by saying that his
framing wasn't pluralistic it doesn't
make sense to speak of workers as a
homogeneous mass and he criticized
traditional socialist goals he called
the experiments that had been done with
Collective societies until then sad
experiences that were causing people in
socialist circles to turn their backs
more and more on the whole Cooperative
movement he even called Central planning
absurd he calculated how much work it
might take for a government to direct an
economy in an advanced European country
and concluded what abundance of judgment
practical knowledge talent for
administration must a government or a
National Assembly have at its disposal
to be even equal to the Supreme
Management or managing control of such a
gigantic organism in the meantime he
argued that socialists were actually
making progress by working
democratically within the system in all
advanced countries he said we see the
Privileges of the capitalist Bourgeois
yielding step-by step to democratic
organizations as a result he said
socialists in those countries are no
longer dreaming of an imminent victory
for socialism by means of a violent
revolution and instead they rely more
and more on work in the municipalities
and other self-governing bodies then he
reframes the goal of socialism he says
to me that which is generally called the
the ultimate aim of socialism is nothing
but the movement is everything this is
now I believe the most highly regarded
mission statement we have for Democratic
socialism the idea of achieving
socialism by gradual reforms surfaced
during Marx's time which was led by
Ferdinand Lal but Marx found it
unsettling and he wrote a letter
denouncing it he said as far as we are
concerned there is only one way open for
almost 40 years now we have emphasized
the class struggle as the fundamental d
driving force of history and especially
the class struggle between Bourgeois and
proletariat as the great lever of modern
social upheaval it is impossible for us
to go together with people who wish to
strike this class struggle from the
movement so Orthodox marxists ended up
defeating LOL it's also probably worth
saying that there was a socialist
gradualist organization active in
England for about a decade before
Bernstein called the Fabian Society
which used an image of a tortoise as a
symbol for gradualism but they did have
an end goal of complete socialism it was
Bernstein's position that the ultimate
aim of socialism is nothing but the
movement is everything that ended up
leading Democratic Socialist thought so
Bernstein is generally recognized as
sort of the father of democratic
socialism the gradualist argument if you
think about it breaks Orthodox Marxism
if workers are making improvements in
their lives through gradual reforms then
they're becoming less miserable they now
have something to lose besides their
chains so why would they risk their
lives in a sudden and probably violent
revolution if they could improve their
lives peacefully and democratically by
working within the system so the further
we move towards reformism the further
away we move from Marx's prediction
strictly understood this led to a split
that was framed as a question within
Marxism reform or revolution reformists
more or less went with Bernstein and
revolutionists stuck with the Orthodox
position Rosa Luxembourg distinguished
herself by publishing a popular pamphlet
affirming the Revolutionary position the
head of the German Socialist Party Carl
kotsky also reaffirmed the Orthodox
Marxist position over and over but
reformism seemed to be the winning
argument in the long term within about
20 years most socialists in the party
moved over to Bernstein's Camp the next
and in my opinion the last major
development in socialism came from
Vladimir Lenin I think Lenin's
contribution to socialism can be mainly
understood in in two phrases neither of
which he said but both I think summarize
his philosophy well the first is that
the revolution must happen socialism
must be implemented by any means
necessary lenon was both committed and
creative he believed in throwing himself
into a problem and figuring things out
as he went something captured in a
Napoleonic Maxim that lenon was fond of
saying he was also a devout Marxist who
treated Marx's writing like scripture
like Marx lenon was was also a
historicist he was driven by an absolute
faith in his own historical destiny the
destiny of leading a Marxist Revolution
lendon was convinced that he would be
the one to wield the conductor's Baton
as he put it in order to make this
revolution happen the first problem that
Lennon had to deal with was the fact
that communism wasn't spreading among
the working class like Marx predicted in
other words class Consciousness wasn't
spreading lenon made this out to be not
only not a problem but natural he said
historically socialism including Marxism
comes from the upper classes from
educated intellectuals he then implied
that the reason why it hadn't spread
among the working class was that it's
too complicated he goes on at length
about how difficult it is to educate
someone to give them genuine class
Consciousness as he sees it implying
this is something the working class
can't figure out on their own so he
concluded that class Consciousness
cannot come from the working class it
has to come from without out so that was
a major break in socialism since Elites
are the ones who understand Marxism as
he argued then the revolution needs to
be led by those Elites in other words by
a Vanguard so this Vanguard of Elites is
as he said to stand undeviatingly on the
basis of Marxism while it leads the
whole of the political struggle with a
staff of professional agitators so in
Orthodox Marxism also called classical
Marxism workers are supposed to lead the
revolution and hold power once the
revolution succeeds in leninism Elites
lead the Revolution and hold power once
it succeeds so Orthodox Marxism is
bottom up and Lennon's philosophy is top
down Elites claim to rule in the name of
the people Lenin's philosophy of
Revolution by any means necessary meant
that the Bolsheviks maintained a certain
amount of ideological and moral
flexibility for example the Bolsheviks
made allies on their way into power but
when they saw opportunity to suddenly
seize power for themselves they took it
then promptly turned to destroy all
parties opposed to that seizure they
also called themselves internationalists
but then leaned into nationalism once
they realized its psychological power
the Bolsheviks also made themselves out
as the party of Peace something that
made them popular among Russian soldiers
at the time but then shortly after
coming into Power were embroiled in a
Civil War as well as Wars with Ukraine
Armenia and Georgia as they all tried to
separate from the Union and also a war
with Poland to give one more example the
Bolsheviks allowed an election once they
came into power when that election
refuted them they dissolved the
constituent assembly ending democracy in
the Soviet Union so for the Bolsheviks
getting power and implementing socialism
as they saw it was the overriding goal
they said what they needed to say and
they did whatever they thought they
needed to do in order to make that
happen the second phrase to understand
leninism is the phrase there shall be no
dissent within the party to understand
Lennon's position on that you could look
at how he defined the word Freedom
dealing with calls for free speech in
his time he said freedom is a grand word
but the type of Freedom that socialists
needed he argued was freedom from
dissent freedom to express your ideas
without anyone conflicting with it he
said socialists need complete Liberty to
reveal to the working class that its
interests are diametrically opposed to
the interests of the bourgeois in
Lennon's framing there are only two
choices socialist or Bourgeois ideology
there's nothing in between and within
that he calls for absolute Conformity to
socialism he says to belittle socialist
ideology in any way to deviate from it
in the slightest degree means
strengthening Bourgeois ideology in
practice this meant Absolute Conformity
to lenon since Lenin system was a top-
down one and he dictated what socialist
ideology was when the Bolsheviks first
first came into power in 1917 no other
political party had ever been so closely
tied to the personality of a single man
as Orlando FES put it in practice this
led to a style of rule that can best be
described as authoritarian so Marxism
leninism is an authoritarian style of
socialism this also typically means an
effectively onep party State Marxist
leninists don't tolerate political
opposition if it's deemed a threat to
the state they also typically use
propaganda to enforce their messaging
and censorship to block ideas that are
deemed politically harmful this also
typically means Mass imprisonment of
political opposition and some sort of
secret police that surveils the
population with Lenin's CA setting the
example for that who later became the
KGB the Bolsheviks also heavily
repressed the Russian Orthodox church
and tried to replace their religious
Authority with the authority of the
communist state so they encouraged a
sort of new warship of the state which
at first was mainly done through
propaganda with Lenin at its head
complete with socialist icons like marks
and Engles replacing traditional
religious ones being socialists Marxist
leninist States also typically take
steps to reduce socioeconomic
hierarchies for example once Russia's
economy stabilized under Lenin's New
Economic Policy the Bolsheviks spread
electricity throughout the Russian
Countryside for the first time in its
history the Bolsheviks also ran on an
all power to the Soviets slogan which at
first when the government was weak meant
the direct self-rule of the peasantry
soldiers and workers another Bolshevik
slogan was loot the looters which was
apparently designed to justify
workingclass resentment and direct
action against the rich this ended up
being a winning formula for gaining
power in the 20th century Marxist
leninists were able to use it to come
into power in China southeast Asia
Eastern Europe subsaharan Africa and
Cuba all Marxist leninists tend to be welfare
for example by trying to provide housing
and full employment and healthare
economically speaking Marxist leninists
tend to be pretty experimental they tend
to abolish certain types of property
ownership and nationalize certain
industries they've also historically run
experiments with Collective work namely
with Collective Farms London's first few
years in office were especially
experimental with his War communism
which even tried to abolish money and
replace it with a universal system of
State passing but their policies tend to
eventually settle somewhere between
capitalism and communism we call Marxist
leninist Communists not because their
policies are fully communistic but
because on one hand they tend to call
themselves that and on the other hand it
helps us distinguish them from other
types of thinkers who aren't inspired by
communism like other types of socialists
and liberals in the Years following
World War II people were looking for
solutions that were more moderate and
hopefully more stable than those
provided by authoritarians in the
decades prior that led to the mass
adoption of liberal democracy throughout
the world especially in Europe the
Socialists that were content to work
within that system were Democratic
socialists and their influence led to
the spread of socialist ideas throughout
Europe it was thought that if the
government brought inequality under
control for example by providing housing
or health care or mandating higher wages
that would make for a happier and
therefore more stable Society the views
of liberals and socialists began to blur
it became normal for liberals to want
some amount of welfare and regulated
capitalism and it became normal for
socialists to be okay with capitalism
and some amount of income inequality so
people generally started to think more
in terms of compromise and moderation
the story of democratic socialism from
World War II onward typically isn't told
as the story of standout individuals but
instead it's told as the story of
political parties the German Socialist
Party had long been seen as discredited
following their decision to support the
Kaiser and join World War I the British
labor party and Swedish social Democrats
instead took up the mantle as Democratic
socialists they don't tend to have any
kind of end goal in mind like complete
socialism and instead they focus their
efforts on trying to diagnose problems
in their time as they see it and solving
those problems through peac Mill reforms
one notable shift in Democratic
Socialist philosophy was to move support
away from Central planning and from the
government owning the means of
production basically experiments with
those policies in the 20th century
didn't work out as well as many had
hoped countries that tried those
policies tended to struggle economically
and it tended to lead to all kinds of
other problems like corruption and even
worse which was a general understanding
that the fall of the Soviet Union seemed
to confirm you can see the change in
their Outlook in the change of clause 4
from the British labor party's
Constitution in 1918 Clause 4 said that
the party's purpose was to secure for
the workers the full fruits of their
industry and the most equitable
distribution thereof that may be
possible upon the basis of the common
ownership of the means of production
distribution and exchange but in 1995
the Clause was revised to say that the
party now wants a dynamic economy
serving the public interest in which the
Enterprise of the market and the rigor
of competition are joined with the
forces of partnership and cooperation to
produce the wealth the nation needs and
the opportunity for all to work and
prosper with a thriving private sector
and high quality Public Services where
those undertakings essential to the
common good are either owned by the
public or accountable to them so you can
see they're adopting a more moderate
position and endorsing some amount of
capitalism the Swedish Social Democratic
party was the most electorally
successful Democratic Socialist Party in
the 20th century consistently winning
elections in SW Sweden between the 30s
and the 80s they distinguished
themselves by toning down ideas of class
conflict and instead pitching a kind of
universal socialism a socialism that
represents the people as a whole as a
party leader put it in 1934 the party
and its policies don't differentiate
between progress for the industrial
proletariat and the agricultural classes
or workers of the hand and brain instead
the party's efforts are based on the
conviction that Society has a special
responsibility to ensure care for those
most in need regardless of who they are
this is people's politics in the word's
truest meaning Democratic socialism
means different things to different
people but generally speaking they don't
want the government to own the means of
production anymore and they don't want
the government to direct the economy
they also don't explicitly see
themselves as representing the working
class they see themselves as
representing people's interests more
broadly if I had to venture a mission
statement for Democratic socialists
besides Bernstein's I think it would go
something like in a world without Dem
Democratic socialists people work for
capitalism in a world with Democratic
socialists capitalism works for people
this video covered the main currents of
socialism as seen through the lens of
the 21st century namely Marxism Marxism
leninism and Democratic socialism there
are many other types of socialism that
either were briefly touched on here or
not mentioned at all for example there
are other types of authoritarian
socialists say in South America and
Africa who are somewhat less committed
to Marx and police States but also
uncommitted to open and fair elections
and rule of law syndicalism could also
be treated as an honorable mention in
socialism syndicalism is seen as an idea
that has been long dead but syndicalists
were influential around the turn of the
20th century they wanted a new Society
where trade unions were the highest
political Authority but I think that's
enough said to wrap things up the
purpose of the video was to answer the
question what is socialism I'll give a
concise answer here but I think the rest
of the video should be treated as the
longer more thorough answer to the
question so if the question is what is
socialism I'd say it's a socioeconomic
philosophy primarily concerned with
shaping wealth institutions or economic
activity according to various
interpretations of equalitarianism I
think that's about as simultaneously
precise and Broad as we can get the only
alternative I can think of is to base a
definition on the principle of
Association like Bernstein did which you
could also call the principle of
cooperation or collectivism in my
opinion equalitarianism runs deeper I
see collectivism as a common solution in
socialism and equalitarianism as the
motivating principle that runs through
the tradition so to Define socialism by
saying that it's based in the principle
of collectivism I think is fine for
basically all intents and purposes but
if we're going to nitpick I'd say that
it gets it subtly wrong I'd say
collectivism is more of a solution and
equalitarianism is the motivating
principle so where does that lead leave
us with the central planning definition
that definition is based in a moment in
time when that was the prevailing goal
of socialists in the 21st century I
don't think that's the case any longer
so I think this is a case where the
dictionary definition is out of date
it's not the job of socialists to stay
conformed to dictionary definitions it's
the job of definitions to describe
socialists as they exist in reality and
that can change over time to sum it up I
think the case for socialism can be
mainly understood as resting on the
following point in a society where
individuals are seen as ends in
themselves where individuals are able to
freely develop and pursue Ventures and
accumulate property as they see fit the
gifted the ambitious or the lucky can
exploit those who are less gifted
ambitious or lucky or perhaps outperform
them so dramatically that those Left
Behind understandably live lives marked
with shame the logic follows whether it
convinces you or not that a better
Society morally and perhaps economically
should have Protections in place to
mitigate that the business of sorting
out what those protections are or how
thorough they should be is much of the
substance of socialism and with that
thank you for watching
goodbye